<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	You may see, Lepidus, and henceforth know,
	It is not Cæsar's natural vice to hate
	Our great competitor. From Alexandria
	This is the news: he fishes, drinks, and wastes
	The lamps of night in revel; is not more manlike
	Than Cleopatra, nor the queen of Ptolemy
	More womanly than he; hardly gave audience, or
	Vouchsaf'd to think he had partners: you shall find there
	A man who is the abstract of all faults
	That all men follow.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	You are too indulgent. Let us grant it is not
	Amiss to tumble on the bed of Ptolemy,
	To give a kingdom for a mirth, to sit
	And keep the turn of tippling with a slave,
	To reel the streets at noon, and stand the buffet
	With knaves that smell of sweat; say this becomes him,—
	As his composure must be rare indeed
	Whom these things cannot blemish,—yet must Antony
	No way excuse his soils, when we do bear
	So great weight in his lightness. If he fill'd
	His vacancy with his voluptuousness,
	Full surfeits and the dryness of his bones
	Call on him for 't; but to confound such time
	That drums him from his sport, and speaks as loud
	As his own state and ours, 'tis to be chid
	As we rate boys, who, being mature in knowledge,
	Pawn their experience to their present pleasure,
	And so rebel to judgment.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	I should have known no less.
	It hath been taught us from the primal state,
	That he which is was wish'd until he were;
	And the ebb'd man, ne'er lov'd till ne'er worth love,
	Comes dear'd by being lack'd. This common body,
	Like to a vagabond flag upon the stream,
	Goes to and back, lackeying the varying tide,
	To rot itself with motion.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	Antony,
	Leave thy lascivious wassails. When thou once
	Wast beaten from Modena, where thou slew'st
	Hirtius and Pansa, consuls, at thy heel
	Did famine follow, whom thou fought'st against,
	Though daintily brought up, with patience more
	Than savages could suffer; thou didst drink
	The stale of horses and the gilded puddle
	Which beasts would cough at; thy palate then did deign
	The roughest berry on the rudest hedge;
	Yea, like the stag, when snow the pasture sheets,
	The barks of trees thou browsed'st; on the Alps
	It is reported thou didst eat strange flesh,
	Which some did die to look on; and all this—
	It wounds thy honour that I speak it now—
	Was borne so like a soldier, that thy cheek
	So much as lank'd not.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 4><14%>
	Let his shames quickly
	Drive him to Rome. 'Tis time we twain
	Did show ourselves i' the field; and to that end
	Assemble me immediate council; Pompey
	Thrives in our idleness.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 4><14%>
	Till which encounter,
	It is my business too. Farewell.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 4><14%>
	Doubt not, sir;
	I knew it for my bond.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 2><19%>
	I do not know,
	Mecænas; ask Agrippa.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 2><19%>
	Welcome to Rome.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 2><19%>
	Sit.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 2><19%>
	Nay, then.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 2><19%>
	I must be laugh'd at
	If, or for nothing or a little, I
	Should say myself offended, and with you
	Chiefly i' the world; more laugh'd at that I should
	Once name you derogately, when to sound your name
	It not concern'd me.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 2><19%>
	No more than my residing here at Rome
	Might be to you in Egypt; yet, if you there
	Did practise on my state, your being in Egypt
	Might be my question.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 2><20%>
	You may be pleas'd to catch at mine intent
	By what did here befall me. Your wife and brother
	Made wars upon me, and their contestation
	Was theme for you, you were the word of war.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><20%>
	You praise yourself
	By laying defects of judgment to me, but
	You patch'd up your excuses.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 2><21%>
	I wrote to you
	When rioting in Alexandria; you
	Did pocket up my letters, and with taunts
	Did gibe my missive out of audience.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><21%>
	You have broken
	The article of your oath, which you shall never
	Have tongue to charge me with.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><21%>
	To lend me arms and aid when I requir'd them,
	The which you both denied.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><22%>
	I do not much dislike the matter, but
	The manner of his speech; for it cannot be
	We shall remain in friendship, our conditions
	So differing in their acts. Yet, if I knew
	What hoop should hold us stanch, from edge to edge
	O' the world I would pursue it.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><22%>
	Speak, Agrippa.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><22%>
	Say not so, Agrippa:
	If Cleopatra heard you, your reproof
	Were well deserv'd of rashness.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><22%>
	Not till he hears how Antony is touch'd
	With what is spoke already.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><23%>
	The power of Cæsar, and
	His power unto Octavia.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><23%>
	There is my hand.
	A sister I bequeath you, whom no brother
	Did ever love so dearly; let her live
	To join our kingdoms and our hearts, and never
	Fly off our loves again!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 2><23%>
	About the Mount Misenum.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><23%>
	Great and increasing; but by sea
	He is an absolute master.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><23%>
	With most gladness;
	And do invite you to my sister's view,
	Whither straight I'll lead you.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 3><26%>
	Good night.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 6><32%>
	Most meet
	That first we come to words, and therefore have we
	Our written purposes before us sent;
	Which if thou hast consider'd, let us know
	If 'twill tie up thy discontented sword,
	And carry back to Sicily much tall youth
	That else must perish here.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 6><32%>
	Take your time.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	There's the point.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	And what may follow,
	To try a larger fortune.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	That's our offer.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	Since I saw you last,
	There is a change upon you.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	That 's the next to do.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	Show us the way, sir.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Will this description satisfy him?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	I could well forbear't.
	It's monstrous labour, when I wash my brain,
	And it grows fouler.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	Possess it, I'll make answer;
	But I had rather fast from all four days
	Than drink so much in one.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 7><40%>
	What would you more? Pompey, good night. Good brother,
	Let me request you off; our graver business
	Frowns at this levity. Gentle lords, let's part;
	You see we have burnt our cheeks; strong Enobarb
	Is weaker than the wine, and mine own tongue
	Splits what it speaks; the wild disguise hath almost
	Antick'd us all. What needs more words? Good night.
	Good Antony, your hand.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><42%>
	You take from me a great part of myself;
	Use me well in't. Sister, prove such a wife
	As my thoughts make thee, and as my furthest band
	Shall pass on thy approof. Most noble Antony,
	Let not the piece of virtue, which is set
	Betwixt us as the cement of our love
	To keep it builded, be the ram to batter
	The fortress of it; for better might we
	Have lov'd without this mean, if on both parts
	This be not cherish'd.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><43%>
	I have said.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><43%>
	Farewell, my dearest sister, fare thee well:
	The elements be kind to thee, and make
	Thy spirits all of comfort! fare thee well.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><43%>
	What,
	Octavia?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 2><44%>
	No, sweet Octavia,
	You shall hear from me still; the time shall not
	Out-go my thinking on you.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 2><44%>
	Adieu; be happy!
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 2><44%>
	Farewell, farewell!
<SPEECH 48><ACT 3><SCENE 6><48%>
	Contemning Rome, he has done all this and more
	In Alexandria; here's the manner of 't;
	I' the market-place, on a tribunal silver'd,
	Cleopatra and himself in chairs of gold
	Were publicly enthron'd; at the feet sat
	Cæsarion, whom they call my father's son,
	And all the unlawful issue that their lust
	Since then hath made between them. Unto her
	He gave the 'stablishment of Egypt; made her
	Of Lower Syria, Cyprus, Lydia,
	Absolute queen.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 3><SCENE 6><48%>
	I' the common show-place, where they exercise.
	His sons he there proclaim'd the kings of kings;
	Great Media, Parthia, and Armenia
	He gave to Alexander; to Ptolemy he assign'd
	Syria, Cilicia, and Phœnicia. She
	In the habiliments of the goddess Isis
	That day appear'd; and oft before gave audience,
	As 'tis reported, so.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 3><SCENE 6><48%>
	The people know it; and have now receiv'd
	His accusations.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 3><SCENE 6><48%>
	Cæsar; and that, having in Sicily
	Sextus Pompeius spoil'd, we had not rated him
	His part o' the isle; then does he say, he lent me
	Some shipping unrestor'd; lastly, he frets
	That Lepidus of the triumvirate
	Should be depos'd; and, being, that we detain
	All his revenue.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 3><SCENE 6><48%>
	'Tis done already, and the messenger gone.
	I have told him, Lepidus was grown too cruel;
	That he his high authority abus'd,
	And did deserve his change: for what I have conquer'd,
	I grant him part; but then, in his Armenia,
	And other of his conquer'd kingdoms, I
	Demand the like.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 3><SCENE 6><49%>
	Nor must not then be yielded to in this.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 3><SCENE 6><49%>
	That ever I should call thee cast-away!
<SPEECH 55><ACT 3><SCENE 6><49%>
	Why have you stol'n upon us thus? You come not
	Like Cæsar's sister; the wife of Antony
	Should have an army for an usher, and
	The neighs of horse to tell of her approach
	Long ere she did appear; the trees by the way
	Should have borne men; and expectation fainted,
	Longing for what it had not; nay, the dust
	Should have ascended to the roof of heaven,
	Rais'd by your populous troops. But you are come
	A market-maid to Rome, and have prevented
	The ostentation of our love, which, left unshown,
	Is often left unlov'd: we should have met you
	By sea and land, supplying every stage
	With an augmented greeting.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 3><SCENE 6><49%>
	Which soon he granted,
	Being an obstruct 'tween his lust and him.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 3><SCENE 6><49%>
	I have eyes upon him,
	And his affairs come to me on the wind.
	Where is he now?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 3><SCENE 6><49%>
	No, my most wrong'd sister; Cleopatra
	Hath nodded him to her. He hath given his empire
	Up to a whore; who now are levying
	The kings o' the earth for war. He hath assembled
	Bocchus, the King of Libya; Archelaus,
	Of Cappadocia; Philadelphos, King
	Of Paphlagonia; the Thracian king, Adallas;
	King Malchus of Arabia; King of Pont;
	Herod of Jewry; Mithridates, King
	Of Comagene; Polemon and Amintas,
	The Kings of Mede and Lycaonia,
	With a more larger list of sceptres.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 3><SCENE 6><50%>
	Welcome hither:
	Your letters did withhold our breaking forth,
	Till we perceiv'd both how you were wrong led
	And we in negligent danger. Cheer your heart;
	Be you not troubled with the time, which drives
	O'er your content these strong necessities,
	But let determin'd things to destiny
	Hold unbewail'd their way. Welcome to Rome;
	Nothing more dear to me. You are abus'd
	Beyond the mark of thought, and the high gods,
	To do you justice, make their ministers
	Of us and those that love you. Best of comfort,
	And ever welcome to us.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 6><50%>
	Most certain. Sister, welcome; pray you,
	Be ever known to patience; my dearest sister!
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 8><53%>
	Taurus!
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 8><53%>
	Strike not by land; keep whole: provoke not battle.
	Till we have done at sea. Do not exceed
	The prescript of this scroll: our fortune lies
	Upon this jump.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><57%>
	Let him appear that's come from Antony.
	Know you him?
<SPEECH 64><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><57%>
	Approach, and speak.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><58%>
	Be 't so. Declare thine office.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><58%>
	For Antony,
	I have no ears to his request. The queen
	Of audience nor desire shall fail, so she
	From Egypt drive her all-disgraced friend,
	Or take his life there; this if she perform,
	She shall not sue unheard. So to them both.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><58%>
	Bring him through the bands.
	From Antony win Cleopatra; promise,
	And in our name, what she requires; add more,
	From thine invention, offers. Women are not
	In their best fortunes strong, but want will perjure
	The ne'er-touch'd vestal. Try thy cunning, Thyreus;
	Make thine own edict for thy pains, which we
	Will answer as a law.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><58%>
	Observe how Antony becomes his flaw,
	And what thou think'st his very action speaks
	In every power that moves.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	He calls me boy, and chides as he had power
	To beat me out of Egypt; my messenger
	He hath whipp'd with rods; dares me to personal combat,
	Cæsar to Antony. Let the old ruffian know
	I have many other ways to die; meantime
	Laugh at his challenge.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	Let our best heads
	Know that to-morrow the last of many battles
	We mean to fight. Within our files there are,
	Of those that serv'd Mark Antony but late,
	Enough to fetch him in. See it done;
	And feast the army; we have store to do 't,
	And they have earn'd the waste. Poor Antony!
<SPEECH 71><ACT 4><SCENE 6><71%>
	Go forth, Agrippa, and begin the fight:
	Our will is Antony be took alive;
	Make it so known.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 4><SCENE 6><71%>
	The time of universal peace is near:
	Prove this a prosperous day, the three-nook'd world
	Shall bear the olive freely.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 4><SCENE 6><71%>
	Go charge Agrippa
	Plant those that have revolted in the van,
	That Antony may seem to spend his fury
	Upon himself.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 4><SCENE X.— ><75%>
	But being charg'd, we will be still by land,
	Which, as I take 't, we shall; for his best force
	Is forth to man his galleys. To the vales,
	And hold our best advantage!
<SPEECH 75><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Go to him, Dolabella, bid him yield;
	Being so frustrate, tell him he mocks
	The pauses that he makes.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Wherefore is that? and what art thou that dar'st
	Appear thus to us?
<SPEECH 77><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	What is 't thou sayst?
<SPEECH 78><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	The breaking of so great a thing should make
	A greater crack; the round world
	Should have shook lions into civil streets,
	And citizens to their dens. The death of Antony
	Is not a single doom; in the name lay
	A moiety of the world.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Look you sad, friends?
	The gods rebuke me, but it is tidings
	To wash the eyes of kings.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	O Antony!
	I have follow'd thee to this; but we do lance
	Diseases in our bodies: I must perforce
	Have shown to thee such a declining day,
	Or look on thine; we could not stall together
	In the whole world. But yet let me lament,
	With tears as sovereign as the blood of hearts,
	That thou, my brother, my competitor
	In top of all design, my mate in empire,
	Friend and companion in the front of war,
	The arm of mine own body, and the heart
	Where mine his thoughts did kindle, that our stars,
	Unreconciliable, should divide
	Our equalness to this. Hear me, good friends,—
	But I will tell you at some meeter season:
	The business of this man looks out of him;
	We'll hear him what he says. Whence are you?
<SPEECH 81><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Bid her have good heart;
	She soon shall know of us, by some of ours,
	How honourable and how kindly we
	Determine for her; for Cæsar cannot live
	To be ungentle.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Come hither, Proculeius. Go and say,
	We purpose her no shame; give her what comforts
	The quality of her passion shall require,
	Lest, in her greatness, by some mortal stroke
	She do defeat us; for her life in Rome
	Would be eternal in our triumph. Go,
	And with your speediest bring us what she says,
	And how you find of her.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Gallus, go you along.
	To second Proculeius?
<SPEECH 84><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Let him alone, for I remember now
	How he's employ'd, he shall in time be ready.
	Go with me to my tent; where you shall see
	How hardly I was drawn into this war;
	How calm and gentle I proceeded still
	In all my writings. Go with me, and see
	What I can show in this.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 5><SCENE 2><92%>
	Which is the Queen of Egypt?
<SPEECH 86><ACT 5><SCENE 2><92%>
	Arise, you shall not kneel.
	I pray you, rise; rise, Egypt.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 5><SCENE 2><92%>
	Take to you no hard thoughts;
	The record of what injuries you did us,
	Though written in our flesh, we shall remember
	As things but done by chance.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 5><SCENE 2><92%>
	Cleopatra, know,
	We will extenuate rather than enforce:
	If you apply yourself to our intents,—
	Which towards you are most gentle,—you shall find
	A benefit in this change; but if you seek
	To lay on me a cruelty, by taking
	Antony's course, you shall bereave yourself
	Of my good purposes, and put your children
	To that destruction which I'll guard them from,
	If thereon you rely. I'll take my leave.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 5><SCENE 2><92%>
	You shall advise me in all for Cleopatra.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Nay, blush not, Cleopatra; I approve
	Your wisdom in the deed.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Good queen, let us entreat you.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	Forbear, Seleucus.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	Cleopatra,
	Not what you have reserv'd, nor what acknowledg'd,
	Put we i' the roll of conquest: still be 't yours,
	Bestow it at your pleasure; and believe,
	Cæsar's no merchant, to make prize with you
	Of things that merchants sold. Therefore be cheer'd;
	Make not your thoughts your prisons: no, dear queen;
	For we intend so to dispose you as
	Yourself shall give us counsel. Feed, and sleep:
	Our care and pity is so much upon you,
	That we remain your friend; and so, adieu.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	Not so. Adieu.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	Bravest at the last,
	She levell'd at our purposes, and, being royal,
	Took her own way. The manner of their deaths?
	I do not see them bleed.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	Poison'd then.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	O noble weakness!
	If they had swallow'd poison 'twould appear
	By external swelling; but she looks like sleep,
	As she would catch another Antony
	In her strong toil of grace.
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 2><100%>
	Most probable
	That so she died; for her physician tells me
	She hath pursu'd conclusions infinite
	Of easy ways to die. Take up her bed;
	And bear her women from the monument.
	She shall be buried by her Antony:
	No grave upon the earth shall clip in it
	A pair so famous. High events as these
	Strike those that make them; and their story is
	No less in pity than his glory which
	Brought them to be lamented. Our army shall,
	In solemn show, attend this funeral,
	And then to Rome. Come, Dolabella, see
	High order in this great solemnity.
