<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	How now, Prince Troilus! wherefore not afield?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	That Paris is returned home, and hurt.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Troilus, by Menelaus.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Hark, what good sport is out of town to-day!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	In all swift haste.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	Is this great Agamemnon's tent, I pray you?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	May one, that is a herald and a prince,
	Do a fair message to his kingly ears?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	Fair leave and large security. How may
	A stranger to those most imperial looks
	Know them from eyes of other mortals?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	Ay;
	I ask, that I might waken reverence,
	And bid the cheek be ready with a blush
	Modest as morning when she coldly eyes
	The youthful Phœbus:
	Which is that god in office, guiding men?
	Which is the high and mighty Agamemnon?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	Courtiers as free, as debonair, unarm'd,
	As bending angels; that's their fame in peace:
	But when they would seem soldiers, they have galls,
	Good arms, strong joints, true swords; and, Jove's accord,
	Nothing so full of heart. But peace, Æneas!
	Peace, Trojan! lay thy finger on thy lips!
	The worthiness of praise distains his worth,
	If that the prais'd himself bring the praise forth;
	But what the repining enemy commends,
	That breath fame blows; that praise, sole pure, transcends.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	Ay, Greek, that is my name.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 3><19%>
	Sir, pardon; 'tis for Agamemnon's ears.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 3><20%>
	Nor I from Troy come not to whisper him:
	I bring a trumpet to awake his ear,
	To set his sense on the attentive bent,
	And then to speak.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 3><20%>
	Trumpet, blow aloud,
	Send thy brass voice through all these lazy tents;
	And every Greek of mettle, let him know,
	What Troy means fairly shall be spoke aloud.
	We have, great Agamemnon, here in Troy.
	A prince called Hector,—Priam is his father,—
	Who in this dull and long-continu'd truce
	Is rusty grown: he bade me take a trumpet,
	And to this purpose speak: kings, princes, lords!
	If there be one among the fair'st of Greece
	That holds his honour higher than his ease,
	That seeks his praise more than he fears his peril,
	That knows his valour, and knows not his fear,
	That loves his mistress more than in confession,
	With truant vows to her own lips he loves,
	And dare avow her beauty and her worth
	In other arms than hers,—to him this challenge.
	Hector, in view of Trojans and of Greeks,
	Shall make it good, or do his best to do it,
	He hath a lady wiser, fairer, truer,
	Than ever Greek did compass in his arms;
	And will to-morrow with his trumpet call,
	Mid-way between your tents and walls of Troy,
	To rouse a Grecian that is true in love:
	If any come, Hector shall honour him;
	If none, he'll say in Troy when he retires,
	The Grecian dames are sunburnt, and not worth
	The splinter of a lance. Even so much.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 3><21%>
	Now heavens forbid such scarcity of youth!
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	Is the prince there in person?
	Had I so good occasion to lie long
	As you, Prince Paris, nothing but heavenly business
	Should rob my bed-mate of my company.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	Health to you, valiant sir,
	During all question of the gentle truce;
	But when I meet you arm'd, as black defiance
	As heart can think or courage execute.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	And thou shalt hunt a lion, that will fly
	With his face backward. In humane gentleness,
	Welcome to Troy! now, by Anchises' life,
	Welcome, indeed! By Venus' hand I swear,
	No man alive can love in such a sort
	The thing he means to kill more excellently.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	We know each other well.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	I was sent for to the king; but why, I know not.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	That I assure you:
	Troilus had rather Troy were borne to Greece
	Than Cressid borne from Troy.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	Good morrow, all.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	Good morrow, lord, good morrow.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	Is not Prince Troilus here?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	Come, he is here, my lord: do not deny him: it doth import him much to speak with me.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Who! nay, then: come, come, you'll do him wrong ere you're 'ware. You'll be so true to him, to be false to him. Do not you know of him, but yet go fetch him hither; go.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	My lord, I scarce have leisure to salute you,
	My matter is so rash: there is at hand
	Paris your brother, and Deiphobus,
	The Grecian Diomed, and our Antenor
	Deliver'd to us; and for him forthwith,
	Ere the first sacrifice, within this hour,
	We must give up to Diomedes' hand
	The Lady Cressida.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	By Priam, and the general state of Troy:
	They are at hand and ready to effect it.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Good, good, my lord; the secrets of nature
	Have not more gift in taciturnity.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	</STAGE DIR> My lord, is the lady ready?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	</STAGE DIR> Nay, good my lord,—
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	How have we spent this morning!
	The prince must think me tardy and remiss,
	That swore to ride before him to the field.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Yea, with a bridegroom's fresh alacrity,
	Let us address to tend on Hector's heels:
	The glory of our Troy doth this day lie
	On his fair worth and single chivalry.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Hail, all you state of Greece! what shall be done
	To him that victory commands? or do you purpose
	A victor shall be known? will you the knights
	Shall to the edge of all extremity
	Pursue each other, or shall be divided
	By any voice or order of the field?
	Hector bade ask.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	He cares not; he'll obey conditions.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	If not Achilles, sir.
	What is your name?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	Therefore Achilles; but, whate'er, know this:
	In the extremity of great and little,
	Valour and pride excel themselves in Hector;
	The one almost as infinite as all,
	The other blank as nothing. Weigh him well,
	And that which looks like pride is courtesy.
	This Ajax is half made of Hector's blood:
	In love whereof half Hector stays at home;
	Half heart, half hand, half Hector comes to seek
	This blended knight, half Trojan, and half Greek.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Princes, enough, so please you.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	There is expectance here from both the sides,
	What further you will do.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	The noble Menelaus.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	'Tis the old Nestor.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	I have been seeking you this hour, my lord.
	Hector, by this, is arming him in Troy:
	Ajax, your guard, stays to conduct you home.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE X.— ><98%>
	Stand, ho! yet are we masters of the field.
	Never go home; here starve we out the night.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE X.— ><99%>
	My lord, you do discomfort all the host.
