<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	They want their porridge and their fat bull-beeves:
	Either they must be dieted like mules
	And have their provender tied to their mouths,
	Or piteous they will look, like drowned mice.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Froissart, a countryman of ours, records,
	England all Olivers and Rowlands bred
	During the time Edward the Third did reign.
	More truly now may this be verified;
	For none but Samsons and Goliases,
	It sendeth forth to skirmish. One to ten!
	Lean raw-bon'd rascals! who would e'er suppose
	They had such courage and audacity?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Be it so.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Doubtless he shrives this woman to her smock;
	Else ne'er could he so long protract his speech.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	He may mean more than we poor men do know:
	These women are shrewd tempters with their tongues.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Leave off delays and let us raise the siege.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 6><23%>
	All France will be replete with mirth and joy,
	When they shall hear how we have play'd the men.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	How now, my lords! what! all unready so?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Of all exploits since first I follow'd arms,
	Ne'er heard I of a war-like enterprise
	More venturous or desperate than this.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Here cometh Charles: I marvel how he sped.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Had all your quarters been so safely kept
	As that whereof I had the government,
	We had not been thus shamefully surpris'd.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	By thrusting out a torch from yonder tower;
	Which, once discern'd, shows that her meaning is,
	No way to that, for weakness, which she enter'd.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	Defer no time, delays have dangerous ends;
	Enter, and cry 'The Dauphin!' presently,
	And then do execution on the watch.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Signior, no.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 3><54%>
	We'll set thy statue in some holy place
	And have thee reverenc'd like a blessed saint:
	Employ thee, then, sweet virgin, for our good.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 3><55%>
	For ever should they be expuls'd from France,
	And not have title of an earldom here.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Pucelle hath bravely play'd her part in this,
	And doth deserve a coronet of gold.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 5><SCENE 2><82%>
	Then, march to Paris, royal Charles of France,
	And keep not back your powers in dalliance.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	Must he be then, as shadow of himself?
	Adorn his temples with a coronet,
	And yet, in substance and authority,
	Retain but privilege of a private man?
	This proffer is absurd and reasonless.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	</STAGE DIR> To say the truth, it is your policy
	To save your subjects from such massacre
	And ruthless slaughters as are daily seen
	By our proceeding in hostility;
	And therefore take this compact of a truce,
	Although you break it when your pleasure serves.
